# Hamdan Iftikhar

Google-Certified **Data Analyst**, excelling in the ability to find trends, uncover insights and drive informed-decision making. A team player combining expertise of a programmer with the creativity of a designer. Delivering key insights & data-driven recommendations through dashboards & comprehensive solutions that will make a difference.

Green Valley, Bhopal, India Phone: +91-9800-454-222 Mail: hamdan.iitkgp@gmail.com www.linkedln.com/in/hamdan-ai Portfolio: www.thatanalyst.net

Open to relocation / remote & available to join immediately.

### **SKILLS**

Languages & Tools: Python (Advanced), SQL (Advanced, 5-star Hackerrank), R, BigQuery, Looker, APIs, Git.

Visualization: Tableau, Google Data Studio, Spreadsheets (Google Sheets, Excel), Python, R, Adobe Photoshop.

**Techniques:** Statistical Analysis & Modeling, Hypothesis & A/B Testing, Regression, Classification, Clustering.

Data: Data Mining, Data Wrangling, Data Analysis, Data Visualization, Data-product deployment (Streamlit).

## **EDUCATION & CERTIFICATIONS**

**Google Data Analytics Professional Certificate (NOV 2021) -** An eight-course program with the industry leading analytics framework (*Ask-Prepare-Process-Analyze-Share-Act*) with R, SQL and Tableau, with a hands-on capstone.

Meta Marketing Analytics Professional Certificate (FEB 2022) - A deep dive in Analytics & Marketing with Python, SQL and Statistics; Sales funnel optimization by performing A/B Tests on the Facebook Ads Platform.

**Google Cloud BigQuery Data Analytics Specialization (***JUL 2022***) -** Advanced SQL in the data warehouse with its architecture to write performance and cost optimized queries. Classification, regression in BigQuery with SQL.

**Integrated Masters of Science, IIT Kharagpur (***JUL* 2015 - MAY 2020) - Ranked in the top 0.5% from 1.2M students to graduate from a top-5 university of India, secured INSPIRE Scholarship and a placement offer in the 4th year.

## **PROJECTS**

**E-commerce store Optimization -** (*Ongoing*) An analysis of the extremely-rich and year-long real dataset of Google Merchandise Store in BigQuery with SQL, with focus on sales funnel and customer retention to increase revenue.

**Recommender System -** Built a movie recommender based on the similarity of their descriptions, fetching posters of recommended movies using an API. Deployed the complete webapp as a live tool using Streamlit and Heroku.

**Segmentation Analysis -** Designed a k-means clustering algorithm and presented the visualization through a live and interactive webapp, demonstrating the step-by-step process on user-defined datasets and number of clusters.

**Device Usage Insights -** Presented insights into customer behavior of a smart-device company by analyzing their daily activity & sleep. Segmented the user-base and delivered tailored recommendations to increase device usage.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Freelance, Data Analyst APR 2022 - Present

Solving real-world data problems from Upwork, Fiverr and Interviews to supplement my project portfolio.

- Amazon BestSellerRank (BSR) Analysis Calculated metrics like ROAS (*Revenue on Ad Spend*) comparing the ad-effectiveness on Prime Days & built an interactive Excel dashboard for BSR evolution.
- YouTube Scraper Tool Built a tool which when given a video URL, fetches the video description using the YouTube API, and without any input, cleans and extracts all the affiliate marketing links present in it.

#### TCS Innovation Labs, Hyderabad, Data Scientist

MAY - JULY 2019, SEP 2020 - APR 2021

Selected as a Data Science intern in India's largest IT Consulting firm during May 2019. Demonstrated exceptional work-ethic & contributions to secure a full-time Data Scientist position. Work at TCS included:

- Independently **developed a novel-program** for an automated workflow using **Python** and **SQL** scripts for extraction of information from text headers, **increasing efficiency by over 20%**.
- Performed dimensionality reduction techniques like PCA to analyze huge amounts of genomic data.